...right we're back build two thousand fifteen.
We're going to talk about windows some really interesting announcements
...great work coming down john she hands with us...some of you remember
him for several years ago talking about
...your also with us add...two thousand twelve with a lash
...fun so let's...talk about the universal windows
platform to tell us a little bit about we've been working on so, for windows ten we decided
to take a step back and look,...assets we had
for windows we have what we had was a whole bunch of operating systems a whole bunch of
platforms that were similar but they works the same and
developers were obviously unhappy with...so we decided to take these all these
separate operating systems that were on the same basic code base and actually make one
That is one operating system to be clear let's talk about the build.
...like you made a lot of
tremendous changes in building these skews of the operating system and talk about that,
yeah, so, I mean the build seems amazingin windows they had to go intake all these
different build systems all these different ways of doing everything because when you build
the telephone you have to go make images one-way when you build windows make a different way
and...do xbox make a different way and, they had to basically combine all of that
...so really we have a start the bottom of the build system and,
get that...common...so then we could build one operating system so then we could,
you know, in the same way go and make xbox make windows
...awesome so this is live as, you know,
ask questions anything windows related one of the things that wasn't really talked about
here gold's what is interesting
the people who are interested in operating systems are sort of, you know,
at the operating system level underneath the platform the
changes that have been made to enable ...just talked about windows I...want to
get a little bit about how windows itself as evolved right kernels probably gotten
what smaller or different media actually so...
As part of that process of trying to build one thing the first thing we had to do was work
on factoring so we had some guys that did great work refactoring the components
in the operating system so that we have a much more and
much nicely layered platform so that we could start small.
And, then add components on top of it so, you know,
we had like multiple bluetooth stacks so now we have one booted stack we
are multiple audio steps now we have one...so all those teams how
...do just a ton of work because you have to run on,
you know, a raspberry pie you know, five hundred twelve...phone.
And, you're also run a huge desktop you...run on xbox and you're going to run on a ppi
neuron pollen...so but,
one great thing about it is that as the teams sort of slim down so
...a great we need to run onyou know, one of five-fold my phone well we need to get smaller we need to get
leader we need to go faster as they did that everyone...because, you know,
so, at a windows is slowly taking up, you know,
less memory getting leaner it's getting faster and,
overtime that will just continue to happen awesome all right so nike
wants to know this is actually great tell us more about the classic windows
...desktop apps and windows store those announced yesterday that imagery to...
talk later at three thirty on this what we're doing is we're taking we have we have this product called
...its application virtualization a ends what let you do is basically
run install like on ibm...
and it captures all the changes that were made to the system by the installer and then
a packages up and...you can deploy it to millions
of machines and there's no more install it's just declared it just gets laid down and just
Were taken that same technique and we're using it to take these
classic windows apps and convert them into
...windows apps nights and I think the thing that people don't realize...going to take a little while
...again is that once you do that conversion you
are now universal windows at right now you still only run desktop for all your
when thirty-two components but over time you can start to add features to your
to your app that are full universe window out features so you can add
...app background task or something and you
could do anything that a universal windows...
and do because you are amazing now in terms of being one
...to apps and jet have obviously...have a different sort of
...process lifetime management infrastructure so it's not like you're
going to get the modern pln or are you when
that would be so for your for your wintry to components your classic components you
...because we're still we're still learning your code run the way it always
debt you're right but if you builds like an
...services a great I...visual studio as I want...mapped out service that's actually
...run in the app container and that's going to have the modern pln and
...what like what we have a lot of experience and doing even
in windows is taking these classic desktop things that we
had and slowly moving them into making the maps so if you look on windows
...the start menu is actually?
And, the way that most people...with the way that we've learned to do it is we start actually
by put building the...sample and running in the app container
and only for things that don't work in the app container do we kind of shell out
...desktop to the full trust...then over time we slowly
evolve it and the mono stuff that's running full trust gets let-you...
lasts until it's gone and then once it's gone now you are just a regular
...awesome...right eric want to know is universal...platform a new
combine runtime for all languages or...multiple...down
...still separatemonetary completely understand the question from that standpoint
it's just like it was a windows...so we have the windows runtime and,
that gets projected into all of the difference
...so right now we support cplus-plus more javascript
me support all of the manage code languages so.
You know, so, that's what that's we still have...that were just pushing it further I think the
...interesting thing is now what we've done is we've combined and we...defined
...api surface that is for an runs everywhere else so if
you're code is only programming to that-you run everywhere and almost all the apps racine built
...do that what some people do...is on top of that say
hey when I'm running on phone rone I'm running on xbox.
There are extra features and...api
...exist there and you can dynamically light up and use those things when you're running,
for example, xbox absolutely so can you explain more about the continuing
feature.
Patrick...now it has all windows
welts I'm not sure I understand that question either so what is the continued
...on what continuum is really the it's what we call the ability to
morph your user experience from saying hey I'm sitting I'm
...a laptop and laptop mode so I've got a mouse and
keyboard I've overlapping windows and then maybe I either detached the keyboard or
islip keyboard backwards and now I'm really intact wanna-be and tablet mode and
the experience can seamlessly more...now what's a great tablet experience no
...windows you have kind of the one-d a model that we had a windows
So, you know, and, then you decide you
...back...into desktop mode from a developer experience there's the only there's
a lot you don't really have to do anything because you always have to support
that you window can resize anyway for so when you going to...you just
...resize command now you're just bigger if you want to you can also say hey
...in tablet mode and if I...tabloid I'll change my buttons
all change location of them...do something to customize it for tablet mode but most
apps usually don't they just they have their experience and that they paint a size
...already works well both for...imacs and that's partially due to the fact that
...writing for platform that was full immersive
...unlike...windows ten where you now have apps running...thirty-two containers I can call them
...running in windows yet and overlapping windows so all right so nike
...think we already talked about this but
...performance good enough to run something like games well,
so, we'll to things I'll say first of all project centennial isn't
abby we use the techniques about the
...part of standing up the project we've been using...is kind of a starting point
but...actually is a separate it's a it's a wholly separate thing and...different goals
...so...these purpose was really and they're selling to
...verbs the id group didn't own the software
...on the code the code was already compiled in some build lab was already burned to a dvd or,
you know, you know copy to...so they can actually change any the code so...has
...has to be like bug for bug compatible has to do any crazy thing that any random
map would might take a dependency on and we're not taking that approach for projects
on because we're targeting the developers we're saying is,
you know, your codes great and we want to use it you might have to make some
...agents like maybe hopefully not a lot of inman all the epsy seen so far like, for example,
if you look to the keynote we had photoshop elements the only thing that they change their was they just change your license
...because they're all licensing code was expecting microsoft side
of basically back to the system for licensing reasons and when they were deployed...
affects they worked at now from a performance standpoint interestingly enough
games are the easiest thing to verbalize or to you know,
to do...environment's games tend to be very much, you know,
they don't...integrate lots of parts of the system and, the code paths that actually have, you know,
that at the or projects...touch?
Are actually the code pass that arts critical path from performance anyway and it's the create
...when you like when you're reading and writing to the file like that's just happening without
...there's, there's no, participation by the by the runtime and when you're opening a file there's a little
bit of participation but that that's not critical right so, yeah, so,
it's easily performance enough for games and,
...and we always end up because we have to test the software
and we always tend to do games first so that when we were testing we...
Awesome man so are...wants to know
rebuild windows ten kernel does this mean there's a new windows driver
model new driver sdk for windows so an interesting question I mean clearly there's been
...in the driver model windows with colonel...user mode sure well,
so, the most interesting thing in that area is that there's now a single universal
driver what you builds a driver and it
can run on anywhere where the hardware it's like you don't have to build one for phone and
then you have to build a separate one for desktop and you have to build a third one for, you know,
for some other device amazing you just build a single driver so if you look, for example,
at the graphics...which are some of those complicated...the graphics driver that runs on
phoning runs it runs on pc the same driver
while awesome and universal...all right we'll...vb used by all
lapse not just absence or I think they probably...on...so,
let's be clear about that project centennial is the thing that's part of windows
bad that will allow you to put your when thirty-two...great
and v is an enterprise technology that has a ton of features that we...
and has a ton of manageability as I said it will do a ton of things that projects antenna
would never do for to get apps marking but, the store
...the like the platform the store are obviously very closely related but they're still
they're still a level of distinction there so these are just
...so even if windows...one you could side load apps and you could install your
own apps in windows ten we made it easier...you've seen the demos with the
...of unlock now yes just go into a control panel you flip a switch and now you
could install whatever you want awesome and that that's true
...for uw ways and obviously first
...apps because as I said they are...some very interesting?
Can you share more about everything that...tunnel will be able to do?
Hey, you're on the...to, yeah, not on the...soI
would you I hope you have a separate session...I work very close to them they do...amazing
stop and I know they have amazing things coming...I would never ever want to accidentally...announce
and for them excellent that thank you so thanks josh.
I like you sure along subplot
old-school seattle right on man ...on both platforms pc
...will be possible to...pc and phone tiles in the start
...start experience.
I think
...layout and we actually don't think the layout on purpose because normally I
like I know about you but I like when my phone I'm really I...a perfect layout
...all this all the information exactly where I want yet and that works great
for my...pc I have a perfect one but they are difference I...of real estate
...you know, I tend to be doing different things with my phone my bc so we actually don't
...it's perfectly reasonable to do it ...
or, you know, it would can be a...feature builds but, you know, my understanding from
...research that they did is that actually...something most people want to look at so
...when thirty-two...that are distributed view the store also updated by the store was
...sort of deployment models change as the update change
...difference update exactly yeah, they're absolutely updated by the store
there installed updated exactly the same way...know I can't stress enough
...it is uw it right so it's universal windows out
...to package and map acts got all exactly the same format you know,
we you...really think project centennial as we really took the you know,
universal window platform and app acts and we added some features to enable the
...thirty-two extensions and if you think about that we
realized that yes it absolutely
is updated exactly the same way so all the great differential stuff that we do where we only,
you know, we only download the blocks of the files of changed on-disk we, you know,
we hardly everything's...only one copy of a file on-disk at any one-time it's a
it's a very efficient pipeline and yes the projects internally projects
...use exactly the same excellence when Iso,
I know that you keep saying...over and over again it's a uw...it's a
...however when you
...out sometimes have complex installation so I'm
going to install my app minimum as part of inflation process...install something else
...service I installed apples and stuff down whatever and then of course I have a complex
the insulation on...so we uw
...to say remove that's gone it's the same for one-thirty to the same for
...to write on rather, yeah, so,...thing and actually the thing that's very magical and I think
you're really going to get people excited is the process for getting rid of your
si forever is you run it one last time I guess you're right you're right
...last time and...no matter how complex it is the you know,
the tool just captures everything and then it
bundles up so it's declarative so there's no more like crazy.
Install anymore and...it just deploys awesome and really,
really xone so is there new media player
...ten the current looks old well we had in starting windows a we created the
video on the video app music app those are continuing to
...get better so, that's really the you know,
that is the new media app but media player but it's been around for years
awesome one wants to know will universe
...support...cf windows communication foundation...a great question so
I believe it's back in now so one thing we've been doing is part of windows...remember windows
...we had all these great new api...and at the time we basically said
if there's an api the does something that we won't bring the...two one four so you think, for example,
about like network so we built a new when rt socket api that was really
...use really performance great api there are
some people out there that said well that's great but I have winsoft code and the answer was
well great I've taken...code intern...rt sockets code windows ten we've gone back and said,
you know, what?
When...a perfectly great api surface
already works inside of the inside of the app container so why do we just...back and we
...and things like create threat like we didn't allow create bread and...we have the, you know,
create bread can be dangerous and great...you can get it wrong and...do all the work for use a
...use the...well but I have a lot of...that are uses great...so we brought that back were
...back tons of api is both...dot net and
in when thirty-two so that'll make it easier and easier to take your existing code base
and, converted to make it a...and of course you had to do that to support the
one-thirty to model in the first-place...the one-thirty to
...runs full trust so insert so it is already using all the same code right
the thing that makes a really interesting and what we've been doing internally as you start with
that conversion process but that's literally step one after that now you say great
well my e kind of like media player my ui kinda looks old and, kind of antiquated,
yeah, let me go build a new you build it using example you run
in the app container...level bunch of other code that doesn't quite work in the app container yet
great that stuff runs full trust over time you basically get your stuff into
the app container and once you...you throw that away now you on xbox?
Now...on hollow what's now you run everyone nice so it's really...great progression
that you can get your...get your stuff in there but, you know, what we didn't want to do
...say part of that is get where your winsoft or get rid of create
...as we added all that so inside the app container for
all the universal apps they can all use those
...beautiful so can universal apps be...and
ran from outside the store not just protesting debugging yes well I mean that was already
...to that was already today but with it was more complicated windows
...one if you look at what we've done now for windows ten now we have
the control panel so you go to the control panel you flip and say okay I want to be able to install
...from outside the store and yes you can call prob in
...thirty-two...run on phones they want and,
the reason being is that the phone doesn't have all of the
...there to actually have all those aps
continue to work so you look at the size of like the
kernel the size of what we call one for the size of the core the operating system
...pretty sweat natural runs...and phone...runs on desktop,
desktop ads just a ton of stuff tons of api
...of things that were built twenty years ago that people still use them and we didn't
...we actually can put that everywhere like that's not going to fit on a tiny little...others,
you know, that has bible mega ram,
you know, and, you know, a gigs of storage space for so because we
...those api aren't there but once you go through that, you know,
you go through that migration progress process and get you get all your stuff into the
app container now you're using the subset of the api surface that will
run on phone that will run on xbox or run everywhere cool?
Can you please explain more about the windows store affiliate program I'm not
...the store team...know-nothing about the windows...fully pronounce art the do you manage
dependency so that you do not have a bunch of different cplus-plus runtime installed for each when he went through
...application or all those bundled and each uw
it also another thing that we did windows...was we actually now have
the see runtime in the platform like a stable version see runtime in the platform
but as probably all you cplus-plus developers now you are often end up with
the dependency on some random flavor of some cplus-plus runtime the one that
your build system uses the one that your...team tests and,
that whole dl health thing where...
apple refine today someone else install...they'd replace your crt with something yes
and you break because of that we have to allow the we have to allow those apps
who have their own instance of it luckily the
when I talked about that deployment technology one of the things it does...single instance so
when it goes the download the app for each file its as well before I download this file and
...bandwidth and ways dissipates wired have this exact file
in this exact same ones and zerosif I do is hardly the file move on so if you
...apps and they all had, you know, like the latest version of the,
you know,...two thousand eight see...bone copy of the file and this
...looked...all directories use it look like every time copies they use nt fs are...actually one
...smart?
Does windows...support transaction on file system by default memory transaction
question?
So, I'm on the file system save I know that
...fs always had that transaction support I also know that it
Wasn't the best feature we ever shipped a and,
actually it's funny because it's no-fault of the file system team the biggest problem we actually have...the hardware in order to
make cheap hardware and still make it run fast and the hardware sometimes wise to
the file system ok so the file system says are those bits on-disk and,
the file and the disk will say yes they are they're really not yet but they're just a
cash but they want they want they want the system run fast so one of the problems we had with
transaction stuff was just that the hardware relied
...and there's really...the file system good no was line so we I know we've
been general we discourage people from using those api as we didn't put them in the m sdk
...not going to put those ems okay because it's really not something most apps never attempted
...on so let's see you're not on the xbox team
...on the xbox so we're not thanks for us...question john if I have an
...device the talk I ot...can I choose what parse the os
...include...size limits...my stuck using the entire os
core some devices...less space and others can the os run a megabytes
so as right now no you can't like take pieces of it.
Other than that...you know, I'm not going to speak for what the outings plans are for like eight meg devices
...they're they on that story they can great right on...so windows
...saws very old absent windows faxes scanned vista will these be
...the final version I don't believe removing anything I'd, you know, we laugh sometimes
we'd love to see that stuff removed because would make our lives easier but there's probably still someone
that using it somewhere and as we've learned before every time we are every
...something someone subsets absolutely well that's what happens when
you have almost a billion users right so...you...install...to
...from the store will remove the only dependencies and regimented info.
Involvebasically what happens is ...remove the app and all the stuff that came down in the app
acts and then additionally we do two things all registry rights
recapture we store...a separate app I that's how we prevent the system from getting slow and
unreliable over time and then any rights that it does to the app data directory we redirect into
its you...updated directory when it gets unsolved those get removed so,
that cleans up the app but if you store if you create a bunch of documents and saved
...in my documents those...still be cool well hey it looks like it's a...
Thank you for asking questions are we couldn't get them all john thank you for coming on always...with you
...we'll be back with the...